[APPLAUSE]
COLT MCANLIS: Yeah!
Google I/O, 2016, right?
Oh, come on.
We're done clapping now?
Is that it?
[LAUGHTER]
All right, we're done.
Hello, everyone.
How are you doing today?
Good?
Staying out of the sun?
Yes?
Fantastic.
Hey, I want to thank everybody for being here.
My name is Colt McAnlis, and I've got to tell you,
I love Google I/O. I love Google I/O, because this is the one
time during the whole year that the crazy Googlers get
to talk to all of you all about the weird stuff we
do that we can't talk about the rest of the year.
And that is fantastic, right?
And today, we're talking about something
that's so near and dear to my heart, and that's data compression.
It is, by far, one of my favorite, most obsessive things
that I ever get involved with.
And I'm so happy that all of you are here.
And all the people standing outside-- I'm sorry.
There's capacity issues.
We'll give them a t-shirt or something later.
But really quick, before we begin, I've got to tell you,
we've only got 45 minutes today.
And that is just not enough time to get
through all the awesome, crazy image compression content
that we need to get done.
So over the past couple of weeks,
I've been trying to diffuse some of this stuff to some other places.
First off, here's my Medium.com page.
Has anyone been reading these articles?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]!
COLT MCANLIS: Yeah!
A round of applause if you've been reading the Medium articles, yeah?
[APPLAUSE]
We're live, folks. you've got to make 'em hear it.
Yeah?
If you read these articles, we get into a lot more depth
on how some of these image formats work
and how to make them a lot smaller.
Second off, of course, is the Android Performance Patterns videos.
Anybody watch these?
[APPLAUSE]
Thank you.
That's fantastic.
Now, if you've ever been interested in data compression,
if you've ever tried to make an attempt
to understand the algorithms, but found
that the math is really weird, or it's
too gnarly of a concept, or maybe it's not presented in the right way,
then good news for you, because Alex Hackey
and I have actually got together,
and we've actually written a data compression book.
And we took a different approach to it.
We threw out all the math.
All of that crazy gnarly stuff that makes your brain melt,
we got rid of it.
And we re-approached how we should
be teaching data compression to modern developers and engineers.
So if you're interested in a deep, fundamental understanding
of how to make your apps smaller for users, check out this book.
Deal?
All right, business is out of the way.
Let's get started.
So when we talk about reducing the data
sizes of your applications for your users,